<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Jonathan Gilligan on jonathangilligan.org </title>
    <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
    <rights>Copyright (c) Jonathan Gilligan.</rights>
    <updated>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 CST</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science Methods for Smart City Applications</title>
      <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/teaching/smart_cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
      <guid>https://www.jgilligan.org/teaching/smart_cities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;University Course&lt;/em&gt; offered under the auspices of the Vanderbilt Strategic Plan, this team-taught, project-based course will integrate technological and socio-economic approaches to challenges facing metropolitan areas experiencing unprecedented growth. It will address the infrastructure and resources needed for sustainable development and to maintain quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By applying a technology-driven, internet-of-things framework to the smart cities concept of urban development, this course will address ethical and justice concerns that include privacy and equitable access to data. Through immersive field research experiences and cross-disciplinary learning activities, students will be able to link the “biology of learning” to innovative, applied social science research experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taught jointly by faculty from Engineering, Peabody and Arts &amp;amp; Sciences, this course will combine lectures on the fundamental material with a semester-long, interdisciplinary group project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Climate Change</title>
      <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/teaching/global_climate_change/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
      <guid>https://www.jgilligan.org/teaching/global_climate_change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course, for undergraduate and graduate students, has three major parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We cover the &lt;strong&gt;basic scientific
principles&lt;/strong&gt; of how the earth&amp;rsquo;s climate functions, causes of climate change
(both natural and human), and examining how these theories compare to the
evidence from direct measurements and the geological record of climate over
the past several million years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study &lt;strong&gt;impacts and possible responses to climate change&lt;/strong&gt;:
How is climate likely to change in the future,
how might this affect people&amp;rsquo;s lives,
and what can be done both to adapt to life in a changing climate and to limit the severity of future climate change. Much of this section
uses methods from economics to assess the risks of climate change and the relative
advantages and disadvantages of different policy options.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the &lt;strong&gt;politics of climate change&lt;/strong&gt;: how does the political process
respond to the risks of climate change, what makes proposed policies more or
less likely to succeed, and what characteristics might make proposed climate policies
more likely to be adopted into practice?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A laboratory section gives students a chance to work with interactive
computer-based climate models and examine data from climate monitoring networks
and the geological record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;syllabus-pdf-files-teaching-ees-3310-5310-syllabus-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;./files/teaching/EES_3310_5310_Syllabus.pdf&#34;&gt;Syllabus (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agent- and Individual-Based Computational Modeling</title>
      <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/teaching/agent_based_modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
      <guid>https://www.jgilligan.org/teaching/agent_based_modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course (for undergraduate and graduate students) introduces agent-based
and individual-based computational modeling with applications to
ecological, social, and behavioral sciences and engineering. It covers
designing and programming models and using the mnodels to conduct
experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;syllabus-pdf-files-teaching-ees-4760-5760-syllabus-pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;./files/teaching/EES_4760_5760_Syllabus.pdf&#34;&gt;Syllabus (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>403</title>
      <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/403/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
      <guid>https://www.jgilligan.org/403/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Sorry, you don&#39;t have permission to do that&lt;/h2&gt;


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>404</title>
      <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/404/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
      <guid>https://www.jgilligan.org/404/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;404: File not found&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Sorry, that doesn&#39;t seem to be here&lt;/h4&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s New</title>
      <link>https://www.jgilligan.org/whats_new/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
      <author>Jonathan Gilligan</author>
      <guid>https://www.jgilligan.org/whats_new/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
